<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Bluetooth-LE | Hacker School Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/categories/bluetooth-le/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-12T21:24:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Laura Skelton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/hacker-school-day-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T20:44:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/hacker-school-day-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had such a fun day! In the morning I learned how to use Arduino to control Neopixel RGB LED lights from Adafruit. It was so fast to get going with this, and the code was easy to tweak to change the patterns the lights would display.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m so excited to learn more about hardware and connecting apps to display patterns with the lights.</p>

<p>I spent some time brainstorming about Mesh Networking with a group. We want to create our own implementation of ICMP (Internet Control Message Protocol) over Bluetooth LE, using iBeacons as a sort of push notification to alert nearby devices that messages are available, and broadcasting messages through the nodes of the network to get to the intended user.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re planning to link the mesh network up with a hardware project using the programmable RGB LED lights from Adafruit to represent the users of the network. I thought it would be cool to make a sort of giant firefly jar with light-dots flying around inside, with one dot representing each user-node of the mesh network. The ObjC iOS app would allow users to join the network and then set their dot&rsquo;s color, which would be reflected in the physical firefly jar.</p>

<p>We found a source for an affordable Bluetooth LE adapter for the Arduino and mapped out a plan for how to design the network on the whiteboard. Excited to give it a go tomorrow!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/hacker-school-day-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T14:25:15-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/11/hacker-school-day-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Things got much more tricky when I started trying to implement SimpleShare, my Bluetooth LE (CoreBluetooth) mesh network sharing app, in Swift, using the new Multipeer Connectivity framework instead of Bluetooth. There were much more complicated things I needed to do in Obj-C, and the app couldn&rsquo;t be &ldquo;translated&rdquo; in the same way as the simpler apps just by changing to the new syntax, since Swift actually works differently in key ways than Obj-C does.</p>

<p>Things I learned about Swift:</p>

<ul>
<li>Optional variables: You can no longer have variables that aren&rsquo;t set or that are nil like you could in Obj-C. If you don&rsquo;t know what a variable is when the class is created, you have to make it an optional variable by putting a ? after the type declaration.</li>
</ul>


<p>```objc
class MyClass {</p>

<pre><code>var mystring: String?
</code></pre>

<p>}
```
* Global variables: It seems that any variables you set within a class but outside of a function act like public parameters for that class and are accessible to read or set from other classes
* Calling functions from another class: You call a function from another class by writing the class name followed by a dot then the function name with its arguments, eg:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='objc'><span class='line'><span class="n">MyClass</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">someFunction</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">arg1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">arg2</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p><code>objc
MyClass.someFunction(arg1,arg2)
</code>
* Init functions are a special case: Instead of calling
<code>objc
MyClass.init(arg1,arg2)
</code>
like you would for any other function, just calling
<code>objc
MyClass(arg1,arg2)
</code>
is how you can init an instance of a class.
* Convenience init: If your init function requires arguments to create a class instance, you can create a second init method for convenience that creates an instance with default values.
```objc
class SimpleMesh {</p>

<pre><code>init(simpleMeshAppID: String) {
    self.simpleMeshAppID = simpleMeshAppID
    self.myItemIDs = ["first", "second", "third", "fourth", "fifth"]
}
convenience init() {
    self.init(simpleMeshAppID: "[NO ID]")
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>In the afternoon, I made a plan with Jorge and Kyle to work on a mesh networking inspector to figure out the limitations of Multipeer Connectivity so that we can build a stable mesh networking messaging app. We decided to move forward on the project in Objective-C while continuing to learn Swift on the side so we can finish more quickly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
