<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Neural-Networks | Hacker School Daily Log]]></title>
  <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/categories/neural-networks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-25T12:11:55-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Laura Skelton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/hacker-school-day-7/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-18T08:15:31-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/hacker-school-day-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started off working on my beer neural network a bit more. I figured out part of the problem that was giving me data that didn&rsquo;t feel right, which had to do with changing the inputs to give an incomplete picture of the outputs to force the neural network to draw more meaningful connections between the missing beer ratings and the existing beer ratings. Basically, I erased half of the beer ratings from each user from the &ldquo;input&rdquo; dataset, and left the &ldquo;output&rdquo; dataset the same, so the network would have to actually predict and couldn&rsquo;t cheat by just figuring out how to compress the ratings down to 10 nodes and then decompress them back to 900 nodes using tricky math.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7neuralnetwork.png" title="&lsquo;neural network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Now that the neural network is actually learning, I can&rsquo;t seem to get my error rate down to a level I&rsquo;m happy with. I&rsquo;m going to keep working on tweaking the parameters of the neural network to see if I can get it to output something cool that I can share.</p>

<p>While my computer was crunching away at reducing the neural network&rsquo;s error, I took a coffee break down the street with a few friends, which led to a fascinating conversation that lasted a couple of hours, mainly about Mesh Networking and Cryptocurrencies. I learned a lot about how different cryptocurrencies work, including Namecoin, which is linked to your domain name and can validate you, and another cryptocurrency that includes its own programming language that can have actually have contracts embedded in code within a transaction.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7dogecoin.png" title="&lsquo;dogecoin&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We went down a pretty complicated rabbit hole of trying to figure out if there was a way to solve some problems in Mesh Networking by linking it with a cryptocurrency, either to validate the identity of nodes to allow secure communication without a centralized server (replacing SSL), or to pay central nodes for traffic they routed in order to reward mesh network users to be good citizens and stay connected to the mesh routing messages between other nodes even when they weren&rsquo;t personally using it.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7torcoin.jpg" title="&lsquo;torcoin&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We ended up talking about an idea to combine a social network with mesh network routing or  secure direct connections by using an app with Bluetooth LE to confirm in person that each person in my inner circle is who they say they are. Each of those people could do the same thing for their trusted friends, and then we would have a network of nodes each with a certain degree of social separation and therefore degree of trustedness which we could use to priorities routing of messages.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7weboftrust.png" title="&lsquo;web of trust&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We left with some interesting ideas and a bunch of reading to do on Mesh Networking. It turns out that the idea of compensating for node bandwidth was discussed in <a href="http://dedis.cs.yale.edu/dissent/papers/hotpets14-torpath.pdf">a recent paper about TorCoin</a>, which would be &ldquo;mined&rdquo; by routing traffic over the Tor network, and then could be sold in altcoin exchanges, encouraging good behavior on the network. We also decided to read through <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wireless_mesh_network#Routing_protocols">an overview of the many previously attempted mesh network routing protocols</a> to get a clearer picture of benefits and pitfalls of different approaches. There is also <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Linked-The-New-Science-Networks/dp/0738206679">a book that discusses the inherent properties of many types of networks</a> that sounds like an interesting read.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7meshnetwork.jpg" title="&lsquo;mesh network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I was totally re-energized by this discussion, and decided to figure out iBeacons so I can make a fun Objective-C app for Hacker School. When I went to the Swift meetup at Etsy, almost everyone I met was excited about Hacker School, and I instantly had something to talk about with the new people I was meeting. On top of that, a few Hacker School alumni came out to the bar in Dumbo after the meetup, which was very cool. The app idea was inspired by a comment someone made that night that Hacker School was like the new Freemasons.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7ibeacon.jpg" title="&lsquo;ibeacons&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I finished up the nitty gritty late into the evening, and should have a fully working app ready for testing tomorrow!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/17/hacker-school-day-6/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T20:48:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/17/hacker-school-day-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I worked on getting a visualization up of the beer neural network (with 100 beers as both inputs and outputs of the network and 10 hidden nodes) that I trained yesterday. Theoretically it should be able to take as input all of a user&rsquo;s beer ratings, and output their predicted ratings for every beer in the system.</p>

<p>I was most interested in classifying the beers and seeing what happened with the inputs to the hidden nodes- would it group certain beers together as sort of tastemakers of that node? I mapped out the top 5 positive and top 5 negative inputs to each node after it was trained onto my beer clustering map, and the results were interesting and a bit confusing. Some of the nodes made more intuitive sense than others, such as this node of someone whose defining taste predictor is that they love pale watery beers and hate Guinness and bitter IPAs.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/6node3.jpg" title="&lsquo;first beernet node 3&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Some of the nodes seemed confusing and a bit random to me intuitively, although the error rate seemed pretty low which seems to indicate that there must be some meaning there. I&rsquo;m going to work tomorrow on training a new network using 900 beers instead of just the top 100 to fill in some of the gaps and nuance of the taste profiles. I actually wonder if 10 nodes was too many for only 100 beers, which would make the groupings more idiosyncratic when broader groups might be more informative. I&rsquo;m also planning to read up on Restricted Boltzmann Machines to delve into some deep learning networks.</p>

<p>I spent a few hours in the afternoon learning about testing in Javascript. This was by far the most formally directed thing I&rsquo;ve worked on at Hacker School so far. Mary gave a presentation showing a simple program in various stages along with the tests she wrote for it, so we could really see how the tests became easier to write as she refactored the code into many smaller functions. We got a chance to pair program afterwards to refactor her Javascript server code and write some tests for it. This was very helpful, and I feel much more directed now in terms of knowing some best practices for writing code.</p>

<p>I spent much of the afternoon rewriting some of my own Python code to break out some of the giant run-on functions into small pieces that I can reuse. It&rsquo;s much cleaner so far, and seems easier to follow since I can get right to a particular piece of code I need to tweak.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m looking forward to cleaning up my code a LOT more. It&rsquo;s helpful to be around so many other programmers I can learn and improve from to write much cleaner, more efficient code, instead of just being happy that the program runs well with no bugs. Planning to focus a lot during Hacker School on improving in that area!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/hacker-school-day-5/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T21:04:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/hacker-school-day-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I continued working through the <a href="http://neuralnetworksanddeeplearning.com">Neural Networks book</a>. A lot of the rusty math started finally coming back to me in sudden bursts of insight, and the book broke the main formulas down enough that I was able to really follow what was going on and how the pieces were working together on a conceptual and mathematical level.</p>

<p>I got some Python code running in the terminal to create and backpropagate a neural network for classifying handwritten digits, using the MNIST dataset, following along with the exercises in the book. It&rsquo;s pretty exciting how quickly the error decreases with the stochastic gradient descent optimization on the weights and biases of the neural network nodes. It seems to learn very quickly!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/5digits.png" title="&lsquo;handwritten digits&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I was bummed to learn that deep neural networks, which have multiple hidden layers between the input and output nodes, are apparently much harder to train than these &ldquo;shallow&rdquo; neural networks with just one hidden layer. Deeper networks are awesome because they can make much smarter decisions and much more complicated distinctions and abstractions between things by looking at patterns in a more complicated way. There is apparently some very recent math (from 2006!) that enables more efficient learning in deeper neural nets, that can train networks with 5 to 10 hidden layers. I&rsquo;m looking forward to learning how to implement these deeper networks, but will have to find a new source of learning materials as this book is currently unfinished and stops after explaining the mathematical proof and conceptual model behind back propagation.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/5deepnetworklayer.png" title="&lsquo;Deep Neural Network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>What is cool about the limitations of training deep neural networks is that one of my early ideas for a Hacker School project now seems like it would actually be useful, more than when I mistakenly believed that many-layered neural networks were easy to set up and train. I wanted to make a modular neural network for image classification, with input layers that took particular sets of images and output them into different categories. For example, networks that detect lines, or shapes, or an eye, or sort by color, etc. The neural networks could be set up in such a way that they are trained individually, but they could be linked to feed information from one to the next in order to do more complicated classifications. Training neural networks takes some processing power, but once they are well-trained, they can process and classify new data very quickly, even running in the browser. I think it would be a really cool open-source project if I could set up a modular framework so that people could add different types of pre-trained visual image processing neural networks that could then be linked up in a custom way for anyone who needed to do image classification quickly.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/5deepnetwork.png" title="&lsquo;Deep Neural Network Image Classification&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I discovered <a href="http://evolvingstuff.blogspot.com/2012/12/learning-mnist-with-shallow-neural.html">another article about shallow neural networks and handwritten digit classification</a> that was very exciting! I hadn&rsquo;t realized until I read it that once the neural network is trained, you could display the relative weights of the inputs to each hidden neuron as a representation of what that hidden neuron was looking for. This is a very similar concept to the discovery of independent features in Non-Negative Matrix Factorization that I learned about last week. The &ldquo;features&rdquo;, or the features the hidden nodes represent, can be represented and described purely by the relative weights of the data inputs they represent. For the articles and topic themes in the Non-Negative Matrix Factorization exercise, that would be the words that describe the theme. For handwritten digit classification, that turns out to be the intensity of the weight of each pixel input for that node, which can be represented visually.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/5input1.jpg" title="&lsquo;handwritten digit feature&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/5input2.jpg" title="&lsquo;handwritten digit feature&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/5input3.jpg" title="&lsquo;handwritten digit feature&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/5input4.jpg" title="&lsquo;handwritten digit feature&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/5input5.jpg" title="&lsquo;handwritten digit feature&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>You can actually see what visual features of the image a particular hidden node of the digit classifier neural network is looking for, and it&rsquo;s easy to imagine that if two hidden nodes were highly active, it could represent for example a top curve and a bottom curve that would indicate the number zero. This visualization of the input weights helped a lot with my conceptual understanding of what the hidden nodes represent and how they might be working together.</p>

<p>This got me very excited about the idea of applying a neural network classifier to my beer ratings dataset of 200,000 beer ratings from a few thousand users of a couple thousand beers. I realized that not only can I use a neural network to recommend beers to users very quickly once the network is trained, but I realized that for beers, the hidden nodes would represent groupings of beers into a sort of taste profile. I&rsquo;m imagining a node each for hoppy-bitter beers, boozy belgians, roasty stouts, and sweeter lighter beers, with each individual user&rsquo;s preferences being some combination of those flavor types, represented in the program by different activations of those hidden nodes. This is very exciting!</p>

<p>I got my beer data into an appropriate format and trained a neural network with 10 hidden nodes (which to my understanding represents 10 beer-taste-profiles), and tomorrow I&rsquo;m going to work on a representation showing which of the top 100 beers activate each node, representing independent features (meaningful beer groupings) of the dataset.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/13/hacker-school-day-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-13T18:18:21-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/13/hacker-school-day-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I continued on the Machine Learning path by starting work on <a href="http://neuralnetworksanddeeplearning.com">Neural Networks and Deep Learning</a> to deepen my understanding of Neural Nets.</p>

<p>I started working on Neural Networks in the <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596529321.do">Programming Collective Intelligence</a> book a few months ago as a way to train a search engine to learn to return better results for a query. The explanation of how Neural Networks were really operating, and why the algorithms were laid out the way they were, was an extremely brief page or two. I got the basic idea of a layer of inputs that fed through a network to return outputs, and then backpropagated based on training data to correct mistakes and improve over time. I didn&rsquo;t understand what was going on with the Hidden Layer, the nodes between the input and output layers, or what was really happening with the weights and where the complicated formula for calculating the new weight of each node was coming from.</p>

<p>The new Neural Networks and Deep Learning book fills in that deeper understanding so well! The pace is perfect, and the author takes the time to pause to explain each step and each formula used in detail. He starts by explaining the Perceptron, the simplest node component of a Neural Network which has been around for a while, and how it could be used to create a similar logical path as a NAND gate, which meant that it can be used for any type of logical calculation since any type of computation can be built up from NAND gates.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/4neuralnet_perceptron.png" title="&lsquo;perceptron acting as NAND gate&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The trouble with Perceptrons is that the inputs and outputs are all binary, and so when it comes to training the network to improve results, the changes are sudden instead of gradual when the weights and biases of a node are adjusted (eg. the output suddenly flips from 1 to 0 instead of decreasing gradually). So, in order to learn, Neural Networks need to use a variation of the Perceptron called a Sigmoid Neuron, which is able to take inputs that range from 0 to 1, and outputs a number ranging from 0 to 1. Instead of a jump from 0 to 1 when the inputs * weights are greater than the bias, the sigmoid function takes the weights of all the inputs and the bias and outputs a number scaled smoothly between 0 and 1, so that incremental changes to the network&rsquo;s weights and biases will make small improvements to the results that can then be optimized.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/4neuralnet_sigmoid.png" title="&lsquo;sigmoid neuron reflects small changes&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I was so excited by this section, because the sigmoid function that was unclearly derived in my earlier Neural Network explorations made perfect sense after this explanation. I got excited and actually graphed out the sigmoid function before I saw his graph a little further down because I saw that it would output larger values scaled to a max of 1 and smaller values scaled to a min of 0 for the inputs. The tone of this book is wonderful in the way that a good professor can explain conversationally a complicated topic and make everything suddenly make perfect sense.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m embarrassed to admit that I got a bit lost with the math in the next section. I took Multivariable Calculus, Linear Algebra, and Partial Differential Equations when I was still in high school, and since I haven&rsquo;t used most of that math since then it&rsquo;s a bit rusty. (Though, side note, I was pleasantly surprised to make use of MV Calc for an architecture project that involved making calculations for projecting a flat print around a spherical globe.) I tracked down my high school textbooks to review some of the concepts I couldn&rsquo;t remember clearly, and learned that most of the textbooks are now available in full online! I&rsquo;m looking forward to reviewing my <a href="https://archive.org/stream/Calculus_643/Spivak-Calculus">Calculus book</a> and <a href="https://archive.org/stream/LinearAlgebra/Hadley-LinearAlgebra">Linear Algebra textbook</a> to quickly relearn a few things, as well as browsing through some other math topics that have always interested me, such as Non-Euclidean Geometry. It&rsquo;s a challenge to stay focused when there are so many amazing things to learn.</p>

<p>The book has a fantastic explanation of what is happening with the hidden layers of a Neural Network, and some overview of what features the hidden nodes might represent.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/4neuralnet_digits.png" title="&lsquo;neural network digit classifier&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>After setting up a certain number of layers and specifying the number of hidden nodes, you assign random weights and biases to each node in the network to begin. You then run the inputs through the network and check the outputs against the known correct answers. Using an optimization method similar to those used in other Machine Learning algorithms, you then attempt to find a local minimum of the error calculation for the output vs. the known answers. In order to avoid doing zillions of calculations for a large data set, you can use an optimization called Stochastic Gradient Descent to pick a random subset of inputs and optimize only on those, which with a large enough subset should approximate the values of the full dataset with a fraction of the processing time.</p>

<p>Super excited to continue working through this book and to learn to implement custom neural network classifiers in code!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/4neuralnet_decider.png" title="&lsquo;neural network decision maker&rsquo;" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/hacker-school-day-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-12T20:55:09-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/hacker-school-day-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started working on fixing some of the bugginess of the Multipeer Connectivity framework in ObjC in the morning. I tried to hack it so that Multipeer would continue working when the app was in background mode (not currently possible due to Apple&rsquo;s imposed limitations), so that we could have a count of how many people were connected to the network.</p>

<p>I also spent some time working on a problem that seems to be coming from issues with lower-level Bluetooth LE frameworks, where there are errors when trying to reconnect to the same peer multiple times after disconnecting. The issues are linked, because there can be problems rejoining the network after the backgrounded app is opened again and tries to reconnect. I suspect it has to do with sessions not fully closing from the first session when the device attempts to start a new session.</p>

<p>I got a much deeper understanding of the capabilities of Multipeer while I was walking through the code handling the sessions and peers within the network, but in the end I concluded that Multipeer is still pretty buggy. I&rsquo;m reconsidering starting with our own implementation of a mesh network in Bluetooth LE instead of using Multipeer, since it seems like Multipeer doesn&rsquo;t really allow us to avoid some of the tricky issues we were handling in CoreBluetooth, and possibly the higher-level framework gives us less power to debug and work around some of the problems. CoreBluetooth also possibly avoids some of the issues with Multipeer not working in background mode, since we can set a Bluetooth LE message to broadcast in the background, and detecting a nearby iBeacon should be able to &ldquo;wake up&rdquo; an app even if it has been closed by the user. Plus I&rsquo;ve already played around with CoreBluetooth with my <a href="https://github.com/lauraskelton/simple-share">SimpleShare</a> Bluetooth LE Local Sharing project.</p>

<p>I switched tasks to continue working through <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596529321.do">Programming Collective Intelligence</a>, an amazing book on Machine Learning algorithms. It was wonderful to get into working on Machine Learning again, since it&rsquo;s what I had originally intended to focus on at Hacker School before I was swept up with Swift.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/pci.jpg" title="&lsquo;programming collective intelligence&rsquo; &lsquo;programming collective intelligence&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I worked through the chapter on Non-Negative Matrix Factorization today, which was actually way more awesome than it sounds. You can scan through a bunch of articles and get word counts, just like in an earlier chapter on document classification using a naive Bayesian classifier. The Bayesian classifier used a weighted probability based on the word counts to predict which category a document belonged to out of a set of predetermined category options, and based on initial training data.</p>

<p>Non-Negative Matrix Factorization is WAY cooler! It starts with the same word-count information for each article set up in a matrix, then factors the matrix into two matrices that, multiplied together, would be approximately equal to the original matrix (articles vs. words). The two factor matrices give you some really neat information about the data set, and they actually extract what the features (categories/themes) are automatically given a set number of desired features. The features can be described by which words are most likely to appear in them. So the first factor matrix has a column for each word and a row for each feature/theme/category, with each number in the matrix being the likelihood that a particular word belongs to that theme, and the second factor matrix has a row for each article and a column for each feature, and the numbers in the matrix correspond to the weight of each theme in that article.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/nmf1.jpg" title="&lsquo;non-negative matrix factorization&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/nmf2.jpg" title="&lsquo;non-negative matrix factorization&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/nmf.jpg" title="&lsquo;non-negative matrix factorization&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s very cool to see how some clever math and optimization can actually allow the algorithm to come up with its own categories/classes of articles (or anything else you&rsquo;re studying), without having any training data or input from the user about what is expected.</p>

<p>I have one more chapter in the book I&rsquo;ve been working through that I&rsquo;m excited to get through tomorrow, on Genetic Programming, which is all about writing programs that can actually modify themselves and evolve the code itself. Super cool!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also looking forward to getting started on learning about Neural Networks more in-depth. I&rsquo;d really like to understand on a deep conceptual level what neural nets are really doing, and this online book looks like a great way to get started. <a href="http://neuralnetworksanddeeplearning.com">http://neuralnetworksanddeeplearning.com</a></p>

<p>I ended the day by doing a short presentation about a beer clustering project I did a couple of months ago in Python. My beer recommendations iOS app generated over 200,000 beer ratings, which has been a pretty cool data set to play around with. I started by scattering beers randomly in a 2 dimensional grid, then moved the points to try to get the distances between each beer to approximate the Pearson distance I calculated by comparing user ratings of all of the beers to find which were most similar (and so should be closer together on the beer map), and which beers were most different, and so should be far apart. I figured out some tricks to break out of the local minimums I kept running into, and ended up with a <a href="http://beerchooser.com/beermap/beergmap.html">pretty cool map</a> of many different beers and how they are related by user preference to each other. (The green color represents IBU &ndash; International Bittering Units, a measure of bitterness/hoppiness in beer, and the blue color represents ABV, or alcohol content, of each beer.)</p>

<p>It was my first time ever presenting a coding project I&rsquo;d done in front of a group of people, and it was a cool experience to share something I&rsquo;d been working on with a group that could follow what I&rsquo;d done and understand what was neat about it. It was great practice for me in talking about my coding work to a larger group, which I have done much more with my design work than with my programming projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
