<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: iOS | Hacker School Daily Log]]></title>
  <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/categories/ios/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-03T12:32:02-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Laura Skelton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 15: Mesh Messaging and ASCII Photo Booths]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/30/hacker-school-day-15/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-30T20:30:06-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/30/hacker-school-day-15</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I completely reworked my <a href="https://github.com/lauraskelton/imesh">ad-hoc mobile networking app</a>. It had been set up so that each time a phone had a message to send, it would advertise itself over Bluetooth LE, connect to other phones as a peripheral, send the message, then close the connection.</p>

<p>I reworked the entire process. Now, the phones are still listening most of the time for other devices, but each periodically broadcasts itself (and becomes discoverable) at random intervals every few minutes. When phones discover each other, they connect and subscribe to push notifications from each other. That way, when there is a message to send, it transmits to all connected devices in a split second.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/14adhocnetwork.gif" title="&lsquo;Split Ad-Hoc Network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s still some debugging to do with connection stability and perfecting the advertising interval so that devices become connected quickly, but so far it is working quite well! I&rsquo;m excited to finish getting the base network established so that I can play around with different network setups that could be built with the technology. I was intrigued by some <a href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/hacker-school-day-7/">earlier conversations about secure communications and web-of-trust networks</a>, as well as <a href="http://ghost.lesiuk.org/AdHoc/network_simulator/">different optimizations for routing the packets beyond simple broadcasting</a>, and it would be cool to use Bluetooth LE to build this.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/14adhocrouting.gif" title="&lsquo;Ad-Hoc Specific Route&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We were talking about what type of photo booth would be appropriate for a Hacker School party, and I had the idea for a fun modification to the booth that would take 4 photos, turn each into ASCII art (green on a black background), and then make an animated GIF image from them that could be projected continuously during a party, inspired by <a href="https://github.com/oxling/iphone-ascii">Amy&rsquo;s ASCII Cam project</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/14asciiphoto.gif" title="&lsquo;ASCII Photo&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Totally coincidentally, when checking out <a href="https://hackmanhattan.com/2014/06/facetron6000-at-figment-2014/">Hack Manhattan</a>, I came across their recent ASCII photo booth project, which takes a photo, converts it to ASCII art, then actually has an Arduino-controlled vintage typewriter type it out onto a sheet of paper for the user to take with them. So cool!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/14asciitypewriter.jpg" title="&lsquo;ASCII Typewriter Booth&rsquo;" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 14: URL Shortener]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/hacker-school-day-14/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-28T20:58:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/hacker-school-day-14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went to the Jobs Practice session on Friday and worked on the assigned project of making a quick URL shortener in 2 hours, which is practice for interview projects. I&rsquo;d never done a URL shortener before, and hadn&rsquo;t worked on web/PHP type stuff in awhile since I switched to iOS apps, so I was excited for the change of pace and the well-defined project.</p>

<p>I was confident that I could write a PHP script very quickly to do the URL shortening and routing, but as I put this up under a subdomain of an existing server I had running for another site, I had to make some tricky changes to the <code>.htaccess</code> file so that Apache would reroute all of the URLs for my shortener to the <code>index.php</code> file with all of my routing scripts. This proved trickier than I expected, since I&rsquo;m not super familiar with the syntax of the <code>.htaccess</code> file and had some trouble getting it to route things properly.</p>

<p>Finally I got the <code>.htaccess</code> file to send things to my script so I could actually write the shortener, but I&rsquo;d like to revisit it this week and learn enough that I can write that part more confidently in the future, and so that I can implement this version better than it currently is written.</p>

<p>I catch short URLs by grabbing the URL with PHP, then look up the short link in the MySQL database, and then redirect the page to the long URL.</p>

<p>```php
if ((strlen($shorturl) > 0) &amp;&amp; $shorturl != &ldquo;shorten&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>    # should redirect to this url

$query = "
    SELECT
    id,
    short,
    url
    FROM urllinks
    WHERE
    short = :shortlink
    ";
    $query_params = array(
                          ':shortlink' =&gt; $shorturl
                          );

    try{
        $stmt = $db-&gt;prepare($query);
        $result = $stmt-&gt;execute($query_params);
    }
    catch(PDOException $ex){ die("Failed to run query: " . $ex-&gt;getMessage()); }
    $goturl_ok = false;
    $row = $stmt-&gt;fetch();
    if($row){
        $goturl_ok = true;
    }

    if($goturl_ok){
        # redirect to the url
        header("Location: " . $row[url]);
        die("Redirecting to: " . $row[url]);
    } else{
        print("Redirect Failed. No such link.");
    }
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s not a short URL, then I look for <code>POST</code> variables to see if the user is trying to shorten their own URL. If so, and if it&rsquo;s a valid URL, I generate a random string of 6 characters and store them in the database with the URL they should point to.</p>

<p>```php
if(!empty($_POST[&lsquo;urltoshorten&rsquo;])){</p>

<pre><code>if (filter_var($_POST['urltoshorten'], FILTER_VALIDATE_URL) === FALSE) {
    echo "&lt;p&gt;URL '" . $_POST['urltoshorten'] . "' is not valid.&lt;/p&gt;";
} else {

    function random_string($length = 6, $chars = '1234567890qwrtypsdfghjklzxcvbnmQWRTYPSDFGHJKLZXCVBNM')
    {
        $chars_length = (strlen($chars) - 1);
        $string = $chars{rand(0, $chars_length)};

        for ($i = 1; $i &lt; $length; $i = strlen($string))
        {
            $r = $chars{rand(0, $chars_length)};
            $string .=  $r;
        }
        return $string;
    }

    $shortstring = random_string();

    $query = "
    INSERT INTO urllinks (short, url)
    VALUES (:shortstring, :urltoshorten)
    ";
    $query_params = array(
                          ':shortstring' =&gt; $shortstring,
                          ':urltoshorten' =&gt; $_POST['urltoshorten']
                          );

    try{
        $stmt = $db-&gt;prepare($query);
        $result = $stmt-&gt;execute($query_params);
    }
    catch(PDOException $ex){ die("Failed to run query: " . $ex-&gt;getMessage()); }
    $goturl_ok = false;
    $row = $stmt-&gt;rowCount();
    # share the new short url
    echo '&lt;p&gt;Shortened URL to &lt;a href="http://prty.us/' . $shortstring . '"&gt;' . 'http://prty.us/' . $shortstring . '&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;';
}
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Otherwise, I return a pretty form for URL shortening that posts to this same page.</p>

<p>```php
<form method="post" action="http://prty.us/shorten" id="shortenurlform"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;label for="urltoshorten"&gt;Enter your URL to shorten:&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;input type="text" class="input-field" id="urltoshorten" name="urltoshorten" value=""&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;input type="submit" class="btn btn-default"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></form>
```</p>

<p><a href="http://prty.us/shorten">Check it out!</a> It was cool how simple this was to implement (the PHP part at least). I used <a href="http://getbootstrap.com">Twitter Bootstrap</a> along with a template I&rsquo;ve used previously to get something nice-looking up very quickly. It&rsquo;s also responsive (everything rearranges nicely if the screen size is smaller, like on your phone) without putting really any extra work into it, since that&rsquo;s part of Bootstrap.</p>

<p>This made me miss doing web stuff and I&rsquo;m thinking of doing more web development while I&rsquo;m here. I find that every project I make needs a good website even just for marketing, and responsive mobile-friendly websites can be a great way to extend an iOS app&rsquo;s functionality to other device platforms.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 13: Mesh Messaging App]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/26/hacker-school-day-13/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-26T20:26:50-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/26/hacker-school-day-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I couldn&rsquo;t get my SecretHandshake app to work properly today after the OAuth changes I&rsquo;d made, so I got to go on a bug-finding detective mission. I couldn&rsquo;t find any code I changed that would make the app suddenly never have its bluetooth delegate methods called, and a lot of error-finding logs that were never called and indicated that nothing was wrong.</p>

<p>I used Git to create a branch of the project from the last version I know for sure works, which I have on TestFlight. I built that and ran it on the device, and it still didn&rsquo;t work! At first I was frustrated, but then I realized that it meant it wasn&rsquo;t anything in the code that was the problem after all. If I built it in the XCode6 beta, it wouldn&rsquo;t ever detect other iBeacons, but if I built it in XCode5, it worked perfectly. Because I can&rsquo;t build for iOS8 from XCode5, that means that I can&rsquo;t get it to run on my iPod anymore at all. Hoping it&rsquo;s a bug in the XCode beta and not some mysterious unannounced change in the OS that breaks iBeacons.</p>

<p>In the afternoon, I got to work laying out the framework for a Bluetooth LE based mobile ad-hoc mesh network using iPhones and CoreBluetooth (a lower level framework than iBeacons that allows me to send longer messages between phones). I built a simple app that lets you input a message and broadcast it to any other phones in range. It was very exciting that it works! I couldn&rsquo;t get out of range of the phones while in the Hacker School space, so I&rsquo;m looking forward to testing out whether the hopping is working (the phone that receives the message broadcasts it on to other phones).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/13mobileadhoc.jpg" title="&lsquo;Mobile Ad Hoc Network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m interested in pairing with some friends to figure out a network protocol that would work for sending messages between phones and for building the network. To send directed messages instead of broadcast, should there be a &ldquo;message received&rdquo; response sent by the phone when it gets there? Perhaps the &ldquo;message&rdquo; is modified in some way by each phone with headers indicating the path it successfully took to get to the intended recipient the fastest, which we could store as a way to map the network. I&rsquo;m also interested in what we had discussed earlier in linking the mesh network to a trusted friend group to allow secure messages to be sent to the people they&rsquo;re intended for.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/13weboftrust.jpg" title="&lsquo;Web of Trust&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The TorCoin model for route signing by each node is inspiring me with ideas for how each node in a mobile ad hoc mesh network might sign a message such that the network could perhaps get smarter about routing messages without having to broadcast everything to each node. Maybe we could incorporate a little bit of machine learning into the Mesh Messaging app (&hellip;meshaging?) to figure out the best routes to try for reaching particular nodes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 12: OAuth Success and Focusing on Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/hacker-school-day-12/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T19:37:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/hacker-school-day-12</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I grabbed coffee in the morning with <a href="https://github.com/oxling">Amy</a> who does iOS development at Etsy, and she gave me some incredibly helpful advice on things to be sure to focus on while I&rsquo;m at Hacker School. I left feeling excited about an idea from earlier in the batch of setting up an ad-hoc mobile network using iPhones over Bluetooth LE, and am hoping to get to work on implementing version one of that project. She also recommended contributing to a larger open-source project as a good way for someone like me who&rsquo;s always worked independently on my own apps to get used to working within someone else&rsquo;s larger code framework, which would be very relevant to doing iOS at a company where many developers are contributing to one project.</p>

<p>After talking through my OAuth handling in the Secret Handshake app with a couple of other Hacker Schoolers, and walking through each step in the OAuth process, I realized that I could handle the entire OAuth verification from within my iOS app, without relying on the external PHP file to request an access token from the server. I rewrote the OAuth handling in the app to use a custom URL scheme that redirects to my app as the Hacker School API redirect, and successfully got everything working. I wrote up an overview of the OAuth process on <a href="https://github.com/lauraskelton/secrethandshake">the app&rsquo;s GitHub readme page</a>, along with the exact query parameters that are required by the API at each step.</p>

<p>Later I finished up with getting a handle on iOS&rsquo;s SpriteKit by implementing a Space Invaders game in Swift. I learned how to attach sound effects to actions in the game such as firing a bullet or a collision between two sprites on the screen (like an enemy and a bullet), how to keep score, and how to transition between different scenes in the game.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/12spaceinvadersprite.jpg" title="&lsquo;Space Invaders in Swift&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Following the repeated advice of Hacker School alumni, I decided to move on from the Space Invaders game as soon as I felt like I was no longer learning from it. I got a general sense of setting up the game play, but I stopped before making a perfect implementation of every feature in the original game. This is a big change from how I usually work&mdash; I feel a huge push to finish and perfect the work that I start, and it feels very strange and pretty luxurious to stop a project when it&rsquo;s stopped being educational for me, but after refocusing on my goals a bit yesterday I&rsquo;m impatient to learn new things.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been having trouble balancing two different ways of taking full advantage of my time at Hacker School. One is that I love being around so many smart, energetic peers who I can learn from and work with, and I have such a short period of time here to have access to that. I love the energy I get from talking to other Hacker Schoolers about code and projects, and there is so much that I&rsquo;ve learned so quickly from other people here both through casual conversation over coffee and in a more formal study-group setting. I feel a lot of pressure to break out of my slightly more comfortable/habitual zone of coding alone to pair with and talk with other people at Hacker School, and to be involved in group projects that are happening around me.</p>

<p>This, combined with an impulse to grab hold of any kind of formalized workshop-style learning that&rsquo;s happening around me due to the reassurance it gives that I&rsquo;m for sure learning/accomplishing something if I participate in those, keeps leading me to participate in more formal talks/workshops that are happening in the space. It seems to reinforce my fear of missing out on learning whenever I see a group of Hacker Schoolers working through something in Hopper (the large group-work room) and I&rsquo;m not participating. It feels like skipping class.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/12hopper.jpg" title="&lsquo;Hopper&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Then I go to a bunch of workshops, and sometimes they&rsquo;re amazingly helpful and right in line with what my learning goals are here. And I think, I should go to more of these! But, other times, I realize a few minutes in that the workshop&rsquo;s focus is not furthering my goals, and I get frustrated at missing out on what could have been coding time, which feels so limited already as my time at Hacker School is flying by.</p>

<p>So, I think I need to just be more aware of the pitfalls of participating in something just because I feel like I &ldquo;should&rdquo;, and do a check with myself before I sign up for things during Hacker School hours to make sure they line up well with what I&rsquo;m already working on and interested in here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 11: Sprites and Space Invaders]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/24/hacker-school-day-11/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-24T20:54:18-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/24/hacker-school-day-11</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I decided Hacker School would be a great opportunity to learn some iOS frameworks I&rsquo;ve never worked with before, since I have time for something with a bit of a steeper learning curve right now than I do when I need to finish a product quickly.</p>

<p>I had an idea for a game/drawing app that would be a simple way to learn some of the animations and custom touch controls that are possible in iOS, so after learning about the different game frameworks available in iOS 8, I decided to start working through <a href="http://www.raywenderlich.com/42699/spritekit-tutorial-for-beginners">a SpriteKit tutorial</a> to get the hang of how to write games.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/11spritekittutorial.png" title="&lsquo;Sprite Kit Tutorial&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Since I&rsquo;m working in Swift, it was much trickier to get the tutorial code up and running as everything needed to be shifted over to the Swift way of thinking before I could test it out. I got a basic app up and running, but was running into some nightmarish problems with a CGPoint init method when I was doing some vector math. The problem had to do with numerical types, and I finally realized that I was mixing CGFloats with Floats, which in Swift are completely different types.</p>

<p>This is what I finally got to compile:</p>

<p>```objc
func rwNormalize(a: CGPoint) &ndash;> CGPoint {</p>

<pre><code>    let length = CGFloat(rwLength(a))

    return CGPoint(x: a.x/length, y: a.y/length)
}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Because I was sending Floats to CGPoint&rsquo;s init instead of CGFloats, the following caused the compiler error &ldquo;Could not find an overload for &lsquo;init&rsquo; that accepts the supplied arguments&rdquo;.</p>

<p>```objc
func rwNormalize(a: CGPoint) &ndash;> CGPoint {</p>

<pre><code>    let length: Float = rwLength(a)

    return CGPoint(x: Float(a.x/length), y: Float(a.y/length))
}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The following function resulted in the compiler error &ldquo;Could not find an overload for &lsquo;/&rsquo; that accepts the supplied arguments&rdquo;, because I was dividing a CGFloat by a Float, which is not allowed in Swift without first converting one of the arguments to be the same type as the other, since otherwise Swift doesn&rsquo;t know what type the output should be.</p>

<p>```objc
func rwNormalize(a: CGPoint) &ndash;> CGPoint {</p>

<pre><code>    let length: Float = rwLength(a)

    return CGPoint(x: a.x/length, y: a.y/length)
}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The debugging process was pretty frustrating, but after finally figuring out what the problem was with the types I had learned a lot about how Swift works and had a stronger sense of being explicit about the types I was inputting and expecting for each function.</p>

<p>I learned about creating a game scene and adding &ldquo;nodes&rdquo; to the scene that can be anything from a label, a player, an enemy, or a projectile, and manipulating them with simple actions like move or rotate. Once I had a sense of the structure of the game, it was a lot clearer how to set up something simple. I&rsquo;m looking forward to learning more about physics and reacting to different events tomorrow.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/11spritekitorganization.png" title="&lsquo;Sprite Kit Organization&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>In the afternoon, Mary <a href="https://github.com/maryrosecook/spaceinvaders">live-coded a Space Invaders game in Javascript</a> in under an hour. That was pretty cool to watch, and it amazes me how simple she makes the code seem. Watching her quickly create a minimum functional mock-up of the game was very helpful for me as a reminder not to get bogged down in, for example, how the Space Invaders look in version one of a game where your focus is on the functionality of the game and getting that to work. She kept this version simple by using rectangles for the player, bullets, and invaders, and that meant that she could get a basic game laid out very quickly. I like her process of development because all of the functions were laid out in a simple way, and it would be straightforward to move forward and edit some of them to add more complex game play and graphics since the basic functionality is already there.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/11spaceinvaders.png" title="&lsquo;Simple Space Invaders&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Moving forward, once I finish with the SpriteKit tutorial game, I&rsquo;m going to try making a similarly simple version of Space Invaders for iOS using SpriteKit and Swift.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/11spaceinvaderscomplex.png" title="&lsquo;Complex Space Invaders&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>In other news, this is the coolest thing about the Q train!</p>

<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/99153550" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>It&rsquo;s a series of lit, painted panels on the wall of the subway tunnel between DeKalb and Canal, that&rsquo;s visible through a series of narrow slits in the tunnel wall. When the train is stopped, it just looks like bright slits, but as soon as the train starts moving, it starts animating flipbook-style. It&rsquo;s <a href="https://signalvnoise.com/posts/2508-bill-brands-masstransiscope-subway-art">an installation that was put there in the 80s called Masstransiscope</a>, inspired by the Zoetrope of the 1800s. Bill Brand, the artist, had the idea that &ldquo;Instead of having the film go through the projector, you could move the audience past the film.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
