<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mesh-Networking | Hacker School Daily Log]]></title>
  <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/categories/mesh-networking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-01T11:20:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Laura Skelton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 15: Mesh Messaging and ASCII Photo Booths]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/30/hacker-school-day-15/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-30T20:30:06-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/30/hacker-school-day-15</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I completely reworked my <a href="https://github.com/lauraskelton/imesh">ad-hoc mobile networking app</a>. It had been set up so that each time a phone had a message to send, it would advertise itself over Bluetooth LE, connect to other phones as a peripheral, send the message, then close the connection.</p>

<p>I reworked the entire process. Now, the phones are still listening most of the time for other devices, but each periodically broadcasts itself (and becomes discoverable) at random intervals every few minutes. When phones discover each other, they connect and subscribe to push notifications from each other. That way, when there is a message to send, it transmits to all connected devices in a split second.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/14adhocnetwork.gif" title="&lsquo;Split Ad-Hoc Network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s still some debugging to do with connection stability and perfecting the advertising interval so that devices become connected quickly, but so far it is working quite well! I&rsquo;m excited to finish getting the base network established so that I can play around with different network setups that could be built with the technology. I was intrigued by some <a href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/hacker-school-day-7/">earlier conversations about secure communications and web-of-trust networks</a>, as well as <a href="http://ghost.lesiuk.org/AdHoc/network_simulator/">different optimizations for routing the packets beyond simple broadcasting</a>, and it would be cool to use Bluetooth LE to build this.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/14adhocrouting.gif" title="&lsquo;Ad-Hoc Specific Route&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We were talking about what type of photo booth would be appropriate for a Hacker School party, and I had the idea for a fun modification to the booth that would take 4 photos, turn each into ASCII art (green on a black background), and then make an animated GIF image from them that could be projected continuously during a party, inspired by <a href="https://github.com/oxling/iphone-ascii">Amy&rsquo;s ASCII Cam project</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/14asciiphoto.gif" title="&lsquo;ASCII Photo&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Totally coincidentally, when checking out <a href="https://hackmanhattan.com/2014/06/facetron6000-at-figment-2014/">Hack Manhattan</a>, I came across their recent ASCII photo booth project, which takes a photo, converts it to ASCII art, then actually has an Arduino-controlled vintage typewriter type it out onto a sheet of paper for the user to take with them. So cool!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/14asciitypewriter.jpg" title="&lsquo;ASCII Typewriter Booth&rsquo;" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 14: URL Shortener]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/hacker-school-day-14/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-28T20:58:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/hacker-school-day-14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went to the Jobs Practice session on Friday and worked on the assigned project of making a quick URL shortener in 2 hours, which is practice for interview projects. I&rsquo;d never done a URL shortener before, and hadn&rsquo;t worked on web/PHP type stuff in awhile since I switched to iOS apps, so I was excited for the change of pace and the well-defined project.</p>

<p>I was confident that I could write a PHP script very quickly to do the URL shortening and routing, but as I put this up under a subdomain of an existing server I had running for another site, I had to make some tricky changes to the <code>.htaccess</code> file so that Apache would reroute all of the URLs for my shortener to the <code>index.php</code> file with all of my routing scripts. This proved trickier than I expected, since I&rsquo;m not super familiar with the syntax of the <code>.htaccess</code> file and had some trouble getting it to route things properly.</p>

<p>Finally I got the <code>.htaccess</code> file to send things to my script so I could actually write the shortener, but I&rsquo;d like to revisit it this week and learn enough that I can write that part more confidently in the future, and so that I can implement this version better than it currently is written.</p>

<p>I catch short URLs by grabbing the URL with PHP, then look up the short link in the MySQL database, and then redirect the page to the long URL.</p>

<p>```php
if ((strlen($shorturl) > 0) &amp;&amp; $shorturl != &ldquo;shorten&rdquo;) {</p>

<pre><code>    # should redirect to this url

$query = "
    SELECT
    id,
    short,
    url
    FROM urllinks
    WHERE
    short = :shortlink
    ";
    $query_params = array(
                          ':shortlink' =&gt; $shorturl
                          );

    try{
        $stmt = $db-&gt;prepare($query);
        $result = $stmt-&gt;execute($query_params);
    }
    catch(PDOException $ex){ die("Failed to run query: " . $ex-&gt;getMessage()); }
    $goturl_ok = false;
    $row = $stmt-&gt;fetch();
    if($row){
        $goturl_ok = true;
    }

    if($goturl_ok){
        # redirect to the url
        header("Location: " . $row[url]);
        die("Redirecting to: " . $row[url]);
    } else{
        print("Redirect Failed. No such link.");
    }
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>If it&rsquo;s not a short URL, then I look for <code>POST</code> variables to see if the user is trying to shorten their own URL. If so, and if it&rsquo;s a valid URL, I generate a random string of 6 characters and store them in the database with the URL they should point to.</p>

<p>```php
if(!empty($_POST[&lsquo;urltoshorten&rsquo;])){</p>

<pre><code>if (filter_var($_POST['urltoshorten'], FILTER_VALIDATE_URL) === FALSE) {
    echo "&lt;p&gt;URL '" . $_POST['urltoshorten'] . "' is not valid.&lt;/p&gt;";
} else {

    function random_string($length = 6, $chars = '1234567890qwrtypsdfghjklzxcvbnmQWRTYPSDFGHJKLZXCVBNM')
    {
        $chars_length = (strlen($chars) - 1);
        $string = $chars{rand(0, $chars_length)};

        for ($i = 1; $i &lt; $length; $i = strlen($string))
        {
            $r = $chars{rand(0, $chars_length)};
            $string .=  $r;
        }
        return $string;
    }

    $shortstring = random_string();

    $query = "
    INSERT INTO urllinks (short, url)
    VALUES (:shortstring, :urltoshorten)
    ";
    $query_params = array(
                          ':shortstring' =&gt; $shortstring,
                          ':urltoshorten' =&gt; $_POST['urltoshorten']
                          );

    try{
        $stmt = $db-&gt;prepare($query);
        $result = $stmt-&gt;execute($query_params);
    }
    catch(PDOException $ex){ die("Failed to run query: " . $ex-&gt;getMessage()); }
    $goturl_ok = false;
    $row = $stmt-&gt;rowCount();
    # share the new short url
    echo '&lt;p&gt;Shortened URL to &lt;a href="http://prty.us/' . $shortstring . '"&gt;' . 'http://prty.us/' . $shortstring . '&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;';
}
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Otherwise, I return a pretty form for URL shortening that posts to this same page.</p>

<p>```php
<form method="post" action="http://prty.us/shorten" id="shortenurlform"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;label for="urltoshorten"&gt;Enter your URL to shorten:&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;input type="text" class="input-field" id="urltoshorten" name="urltoshorten" value=""&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;input type="submit" class="btn btn-default"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></form>
```</p>

<p><a href="http://prty.us/shorten">Check it out!</a> It was cool how simple this was to implement (the PHP part at least). I used <a href="http://getbootstrap.com">Twitter Bootstrap</a> along with a template I&rsquo;ve used previously to get something nice-looking up very quickly. It&rsquo;s also responsive (everything rearranges nicely if the screen size is smaller, like on your phone) without putting really any extra work into it, since that&rsquo;s part of Bootstrap.</p>

<p>This made me miss doing web stuff and I&rsquo;m thinking of doing more web development while I&rsquo;m here. I find that every project I make needs a good website even just for marketing, and responsive mobile-friendly websites can be a great way to extend an iOS app&rsquo;s functionality to other device platforms.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 13: Mesh Messaging App]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/26/hacker-school-day-13/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-26T20:26:50-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/26/hacker-school-day-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I couldn&rsquo;t get my SecretHandshake app to work properly today after the OAuth changes I&rsquo;d made, so I got to go on a bug-finding detective mission. I couldn&rsquo;t find any code I changed that would make the app suddenly never have its bluetooth delegate methods called, and a lot of error-finding logs that were never called and indicated that nothing was wrong.</p>

<p>I used Git to create a branch of the project from the last version I know for sure works, which I have on TestFlight. I built that and ran it on the device, and it still didn&rsquo;t work! At first I was frustrated, but then I realized that it meant it wasn&rsquo;t anything in the code that was the problem after all. If I built it in the XCode6 beta, it wouldn&rsquo;t ever detect other iBeacons, but if I built it in XCode5, it worked perfectly. Because I can&rsquo;t build for iOS8 from XCode5, that means that I can&rsquo;t get it to run on my iPod anymore at all. Hoping it&rsquo;s a bug in the XCode beta and not some mysterious unannounced change in the OS that breaks iBeacons.</p>

<p>In the afternoon, I got to work laying out the framework for a Bluetooth LE based mobile ad-hoc mesh network using iPhones and CoreBluetooth (a lower level framework than iBeacons that allows me to send longer messages between phones). I built a simple app that lets you input a message and broadcast it to any other phones in range. It was very exciting that it works! I couldn&rsquo;t get out of range of the phones while in the Hacker School space, so I&rsquo;m looking forward to testing out whether the hopping is working (the phone that receives the message broadcasts it on to other phones).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/13mobileadhoc.jpg" title="&lsquo;Mobile Ad Hoc Network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m interested in pairing with some friends to figure out a network protocol that would work for sending messages between phones and for building the network. To send directed messages instead of broadcast, should there be a &ldquo;message received&rdquo; response sent by the phone when it gets there? Perhaps the &ldquo;message&rdquo; is modified in some way by each phone with headers indicating the path it successfully took to get to the intended recipient the fastest, which we could store as a way to map the network. I&rsquo;m also interested in what we had discussed earlier in linking the mesh network to a trusted friend group to allow secure messages to be sent to the people they&rsquo;re intended for.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/13weboftrust.jpg" title="&lsquo;Web of Trust&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The TorCoin model for route signing by each node is inspiring me with ideas for how each node in a mobile ad hoc mesh network might sign a message such that the network could perhaps get smarter about routing messages without having to broadcast everything to each node. Maybe we could incorporate a little bit of machine learning into the Mesh Messaging app (&hellip;meshaging?) to figure out the best routes to try for reaching particular nodes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 7: Mesh Networking, Cryptocurrencies, and iBeacons]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/hacker-school-day-7/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-18T08:15:31-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/18/hacker-school-day-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started off working on my beer neural network a bit more. I figured out part of the problem that was giving me data that didn&rsquo;t feel right, which had to do with changing the inputs to give an incomplete picture of the outputs to force the neural network to draw more meaningful connections between the missing beer ratings and the existing beer ratings. Basically, I erased half of the beer ratings from each user from the &ldquo;input&rdquo; dataset, and left the &ldquo;output&rdquo; dataset the same, so the network would have to actually predict and couldn&rsquo;t cheat by just figuring out how to compress the ratings down to 10 nodes and then decompress them back to 900 nodes using tricky math.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7neuralnetwork.png" title="&lsquo;neural network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Now that the neural network is actually learning, I can&rsquo;t seem to get my error rate down to a level I&rsquo;m happy with. I&rsquo;m going to keep working on tweaking the parameters of the neural network to see if I can get it to output something cool that I can share.</p>

<p>While my computer was crunching away at reducing the neural network&rsquo;s error, I took a coffee break down the street with a few friends, which led to a fascinating conversation that lasted a couple of hours, mainly about Mesh Networking and Cryptocurrencies. I learned a lot about how different cryptocurrencies work, including Namecoin, which is linked to your domain name and can validate you, and another cryptocurrency that includes its own programming language that can have actually have contracts embedded in code within a transaction.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7dogecoin.png" title="&lsquo;dogecoin&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We went down a pretty complicated rabbit hole of trying to figure out if there was a way to solve some problems in Mesh Networking by linking it with a cryptocurrency, either to validate the identity of nodes to allow secure communication without a centralized server (replacing SSL), or to pay central nodes for traffic they routed in order to reward mesh network users to be good citizens and stay connected to the mesh routing messages between other nodes even when they weren&rsquo;t personally using it.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7torcoin.jpg" title="&lsquo;torcoin&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We ended up talking about an idea to combine a social network with mesh network routing or  secure direct connections by using an app with Bluetooth LE to confirm in person that each person in my inner circle is who they say they are. Each of those people could do the same thing for their trusted friends, and then we would have a network of nodes each with a certain degree of social separation and therefore degree of trustedness which we could use to priorities routing of messages.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7weboftrust.png" title="&lsquo;web of trust&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>We left with some interesting ideas and a bunch of reading to do on Mesh Networking. It turns out that the idea of compensating for node bandwidth was discussed in <a href="http://dedis.cs.yale.edu/dissent/papers/hotpets14-torpath.pdf">a recent paper about TorCoin</a>, which would be &ldquo;mined&rdquo; by routing traffic over the Tor network, and then could be sold in altcoin exchanges, encouraging good behavior on the network. We also decided to read through <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wireless_mesh_network#Routing_protocols">an overview of the many previously attempted mesh network routing protocols</a> to get a clearer picture of benefits and pitfalls of different approaches. There is also <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Linked-The-New-Science-Networks/dp/0738206679">a book that discusses the inherent properties of many types of networks</a> that sounds like an interesting read.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7meshnetwork.jpg" title="&lsquo;mesh network&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I was totally re-energized by this discussion, and decided to figure out iBeacons so I can make a fun Objective-C app for Hacker School. When I went to the Swift meetup at Etsy, almost everyone I met was excited about Hacker School, and I instantly had something to talk about with the new people I was meeting. On top of that, a few Hacker School alumni came out to the bar in Dumbo after the meetup, which was very cool. The app idea was inspired by a comment someone made that night that Hacker School was like the new Freemasons.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/7ibeacon.jpg" title="&lsquo;ibeacons&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I finished up the nitty gritty late into the evening, and should have a fully working app ready for testing tomorrow!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Day 3: Non-Negative Matrix Factorization and Beer Clustering]]></title>
    <link href="http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/hacker-school-day-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-12T20:55:09-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lauraskelton.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/hacker-school-day-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started working on fixing some of the bugginess of the Multipeer Connectivity framework in ObjC in the morning. I tried to hack it so that Multipeer would continue working when the app was in background mode (not currently possible due to Apple&rsquo;s imposed limitations), so that we could have a count of how many people were connected to the network.</p>

<p>I also spent some time working on a problem that seems to be coming from issues with lower-level Bluetooth LE frameworks, where there are errors when trying to reconnect to the same peer multiple times after disconnecting. The issues are linked, because there can be problems rejoining the network after the backgrounded app is opened again and tries to reconnect. I suspect it has to do with sessions not fully closing from the first session when the device attempts to start a new session.</p>

<p>I got a much deeper understanding of the capabilities of Multipeer while I was walking through the code handling the sessions and peers within the network, but in the end I concluded that Multipeer is still pretty buggy. I&rsquo;m reconsidering starting with our own implementation of a mesh network in Bluetooth LE instead of using Multipeer, since it seems like Multipeer doesn&rsquo;t really allow us to avoid some of the tricky issues we were handling in CoreBluetooth, and possibly the higher-level framework gives us less power to debug and work around some of the problems. CoreBluetooth also possibly avoids some of the issues with Multipeer not working in background mode, since we can set a Bluetooth LE message to broadcast in the background, and detecting a nearby iBeacon should be able to &ldquo;wake up&rdquo; an app even if it has been closed by the user. Plus I&rsquo;ve already played around with CoreBluetooth with my <a href="https://github.com/lauraskelton/simple-share">SimpleShare</a> Bluetooth LE Local Sharing project.</p>

<p>I switched tasks to continue working through <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596529321.do">Programming Collective Intelligence</a>, an amazing book on Machine Learning algorithms. It was wonderful to get into working on Machine Learning again, since it&rsquo;s what I had originally intended to focus on at Hacker School before I was swept up with Swift.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/pci.jpg" title="&lsquo;programming collective intelligence&rsquo; &lsquo;programming collective intelligence&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I worked through the chapter on Non-Negative Matrix Factorization today, which was actually way more awesome than it sounds. You can scan through a bunch of articles and get word counts, just like in an earlier chapter on document classification using a naive Bayesian classifier. The Bayesian classifier used a weighted probability based on the word counts to predict which category a document belonged to out of a set of predetermined category options, and based on initial training data.</p>

<p>Non-Negative Matrix Factorization is WAY cooler! It starts with the same word-count information for each article set up in a matrix, then factors the matrix into two matrices that, multiplied together, would be approximately equal to the original matrix (articles vs. words). The two factor matrices give you some really neat information about the data set, and they actually extract what the features (categories/themes) are automatically given a set number of desired features. The features can be described by which words are most likely to appear in them. So the first factor matrix has a column for each word and a row for each feature/theme/category, with each number in the matrix being the likelihood that a particular word belongs to that theme, and the second factor matrix has a row for each article and a column for each feature, and the numbers in the matrix correspond to the weight of each theme in that article.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/nmf1.jpg" title="&lsquo;non-negative matrix factorization&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/nmf2.jpg" title="&lsquo;non-negative matrix factorization&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/nmf.jpg" title="&lsquo;non-negative matrix factorization&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s very cool to see how some clever math and optimization can actually allow the algorithm to come up with its own categories/classes of articles (or anything else you&rsquo;re studying), without having any training data or input from the user about what is expected.</p>

<p>I have one more chapter in the book I&rsquo;ve been working through that I&rsquo;m excited to get through tomorrow, on Genetic Programming, which is all about writing programs that can actually modify themselves and evolve the code itself. Super cool!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also looking forward to getting started on learning about Neural Networks more in-depth. I&rsquo;d really like to understand on a deep conceptual level what neural nets are really doing, and this online book looks like a great way to get started. <a href="http://neuralnetworksanddeeplearning.com">http://neuralnetworksanddeeplearning.com</a></p>

<p>I ended the day by doing a short presentation about a beer clustering project I did a couple of months ago in Python. My beer recommendations iOS app generated over 200,000 beer ratings, which has been a pretty cool data set to play around with. I started by scattering beers randomly in a 2 dimensional grid, then moved the points to try to get the distances between each beer to approximate the Pearson distance I calculated by comparing user ratings of all of the beers to find which were most similar (and so should be closer together on the beer map), and which beers were most different, and so should be far apart. I figured out some tricks to break out of the local minimums I kept running into, and ended up with a <a href="http://beerchooser.com/beermap/beergmap.html">pretty cool map</a> of many different beers and how they are related by user preference to each other. (The green color represents IBU &ndash; International Bittering Units, a measure of bitterness/hoppiness in beer, and the blue color represents ABV, or alcohol content, of each beer.)</p>

<p>It was my first time ever presenting a coding project I&rsquo;d done in front of a group of people, and it was a cool experience to share something I&rsquo;d been working on with a group that could follow what I&rsquo;d done and understand what was neat about it. It was great practice for me in talking about my coding work to a larger group, which I have done much more with my design work than with my programming projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
